<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><text><div>

<head><rs ref="#rs-m">Varnish</rs> for panels</head>

<p>Take a <rs ref="#rs-ms">lb</rs> of <rs ref="#rs-m"><rs ref="#rs-pl">Venice</rs> turpentine</rs> &amp; heat
it in a <rs ref="#rs-tl">pot</rs> until it simmers, and put in half a <rs ref="#rs-ms">lb</rs> of
the <rs ref="#rs-m">turpentine oil</rs> of the whitest you can find, and stir it
together well on a <rs ref="#rs-m">charcoal</rs> fire and take it off immediately. And
<del><rs ref="#rs-fr">elle</rs></del> it is done. But if it seems too thick to you,
add in a little more <rs ref="#rs-m">oil</rs>. Similarly if it is too clear, you can
thicken it by putting in a little <rs ref="#rs-m">turpentine</rs>. Thus you will give it
whatever body you want. It could be made well without fire, but, when
heated, it is more desiccative. It is appropriate for panel paintings
and other painted things without corrupting the colors or yellowing. And
it dries both <rs ref="#rs-env">in the shade</rs> and <rs ref="#rs-env">in the sun</rs>, and
<rs ref="#rs-tmp">overnight</rs>, and <rs ref="#rs-tmp">during the winter</rs> as well as
<rs ref="#rs-tmp">in the summer</rs>. It is commonly sold 15 <rs ref="#rs-cn">sous</rs> a
<rs ref="#rs-ms">lb</rs>.</p>

<p rend="left-bottom" render="tall">




A little more <rs ref="#rs-m">turpentine</rs> than <rs ref="#rs-m">turpentine oil</rs> is needed in
order to give body to the <rs ref="#rs-m">varnish</rs>, which needs to be applied with
the <rs ref="#rs-tl"><rs ref="#rs-bp">finger</rs></rs> in order to spread it thinner and less thick,
for when it is thick, it turns yellow and sticks. One does not
<rs ref="#rs-m">varnish</rs> to make paintings shine, for it just takes the light out
of them.</p>

</div>



<div>
        
<p rend="left-middle" render="wide">    
But it is used to heighten colors which have soaked in and to keep them
from dust. <rs ref="#rs-m">Mastic varnish</rs> does not resist <rs ref="#rs-env">rain</rs>,
whereas that of <rs ref="#rs-m">oil</rs> and <rs ref="#rs-m">rosin</rs> does.</p>  
</div>
    
</text>